<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lucas' Recipe Repo</title>
    <description>Recipes for all of my food pictures.</description>
    <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 20:02:37 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2021 20:02:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pasta with garden tomatoes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enough pasta and tomato sauce recipes have influenced this simple recipe&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;that I’m willing to call it my own - though let’s not confuse that with&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;calling it “unique.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week or two in June, July, and August, there are 2-4 lbs of tomoatoes to pick and eat
in the garden I started during the summer of 2020. This recipe was built as a way
to use up the tomatoes without too much time or effort needed. It’s quick enough that
it could be made for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container-fluid&quot; style=&quot;padding: 0em;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align: center;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh cherry tomatoes (~2 lbs in photos)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kosher salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Garlic, sliced (~3 cloves)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Freshly ground black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fresh basil (8-12 leaves plus more for garnish)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pasta for 1-4 people (I prefer tubes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parmesan cheese for garnish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot; style=&quot;padding: 1.5em&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/garden-sauce-pasta/pasta-garden-tomatoes-extra.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tomatoes on the vine.&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Tomatoes on the vine.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 starts=&quot;1&quot; id=&quot;recipe&quot;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get your pasta cooking until just short of al dente. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seriouseats.com/ask-the-food-lab-can-i-start-pasta-in-cold-water&quot;&gt;Kenji has a great Serious Eats article&lt;/a&gt; on
the myths behind cooking pasta. TL;DR You can heat your pasta and water at the same time as long as it’s (a) not fresh made and (b) not long (ex. spaghetti).
I prefer this recipe with boxed penne or rigatoni so I’m in the clear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container-fluid&quot; style=&quot;padding: 0em;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align: center;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;
&lt;ol starts=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Place a cast iron skillet or dutch oven on medium to high heat. While heating, wash and dry the tomatoes
and pick the stems, peel and thinly slice the garlic cloves, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?channel=fs&amp;amp;client=ubuntu&amp;amp;q=chiffonade&quot;&gt;chiffonade&lt;/a&gt; the basil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot; style=&quot;padding: 1.5em&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/garden-sauce-pasta/pasta-garden-tomatoes-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tomatoes collected from my garden and used in this recipe&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Tomatoes collected from my garden and used in this recipe&lt;/figcaption&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add enough olive oil to the hot pan to create a thin layer and immediately add the tomatoes. Reduce the temperature slightly and add kosher salt.
Be careful of hot oil splattering
and feel free to cover the tomatoes for a bit if the oil is making a mess outside of the pan. The tomatoes should start to burst after about five minutes.
Encourage them a bit by pressing on them with the back of a wooden spoon or spatula. Let them continue to cook for about five minutes more or until 
a sauce is formed (see images below for reference).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/garden-sauce-pasta/pasta-garden-tomatoes-3b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tomatoes after about 5 minutes on heat.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Tomatoes after about 5 minutes on heat.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/garden-sauce-pasta/pasta-garden-tomatoes-3c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tomatoes after about 10 minutes on heat.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Tomatoes after about 10 minutes on heat.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the tomatoes have mostly broken down, add the garlic, black pepper, and basil. Also add a tablespoon or two of the pasta cooking water.
The starches will help thicken your sauce. Allow the sauce mixture to simmer for 5-10 minutes at a low heat, stirring occasionally so the
contents near the bottom of the pan don’t burn or stick.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If sticking occurs, add some pasta water in that area and scrape up the sticking bits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The garlic is added in this step so that it gently boils to make soft, plump garlic nuggets.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you haven’t already, drain your pasta and add the tomato sauce to the pasta until you have the ratio you prefer. Make sure the
sauce is still hot so the pasta will cook through the final step to al dente. Allow any extra sauce to cool before storing. 
Plate the pasta+sauce and top with fresh basil, black pepper, and parmesan cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/garden-sauce-pasta/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/garden-sauce-pasta/</guid>
        
        
        <category>original</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Buffalo Chicken Wings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Credit for this recipe goes to Chef John at Foooood Wishes dot com. I’ve made some slight modifications&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;which I will mark below but you can find the original&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;recipe &lt;a href=&quot;https://foodwishes.blogspot.com/2015/01/crispy-honey-sriracha-chicken-wings.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;the accompanying video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BDVg0u2YQ7Q&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was debating titling this “Chicken Wings &lt;u&gt;in the Oven&lt;/u&gt;” until I realized
it’s really irrelevant. “In the Oven” is not some sort of compromise or condition
for these wings. This is the easiest and &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; way to make wings at home and
I’d argue they turn out better than wings you get at most restaurants - and they
are much cheaper!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I repeat the recipe from Chef John below with some slight modifications. I also separate out
the wing preparation from the sauce since I forgo the honey sriracha for classic Buffalo sauce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before that, I want to point out the important food chemistry that makes this recipe so good
the &lt;em&gt;Maillard Reaction&lt;/em&gt; which is encouraged by the baking powder (or really, it’s the baking soda in the baking powder).
This addition is lowering the pH of the outside of the wing and encouraging the same reaction that
happens when you sear a steak or bake cookies (with baking powder/soda) - 
browning and crisping that tests really good. Without this addition, the wings would be soggy like most
of the oven-based ones you find at restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read more Maillard reaction in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seriouseats.com/what-is-maillard-reaction-cooking-science&quot;&gt;this Serious Eats post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chicken-wings&quot;&gt;Chicken wings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.5 lbs of chicken wings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 tbps baking powder&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;1/2 tbsp kosher salt (half of what Chef John uses)&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 tsp fresh ground black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 tsp smoked paprika&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preheat oven to 425 F. Place parchment paper on a baking sheet.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The original recipe uses a wire rack over aluminum foil. This probably works
 best but my wire racks cannot go beyond 400 F. I’ve found the parchment paper works well to avoid sticking though and the wings cook
 perfectly well.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If needed, breakdown the wings into three portions: tips, flats, and drums. Reserve the tips for stock or throw away. Place the
flats and drums in a large bowl.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine the dry ingredients in a small bowl to create a rub. Sprinkle over the flats and drums and toss to coat. Place on the 
parchment paper-lined baking sheet(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/wings/wings-tossed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wings broken down and coated, ready for the oven.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Wings broken down and coated, ready for the oven.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bake in the pre-heated oven for three intervals of 20 minutes (60 minutes total). After each 20 minute block, turn the wings
over.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;On the first and second turns, they may look dry and powdery. That’s okay - keep turning and baking.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The final product should be browned and crispy. Use “Chef John’s fork test” to check (scrape a fork against the skin to check for crispiness).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buffalo-sauce&quot;&gt;Buffalo sauce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chef John’s honey sriracha sauce is plenty good but I really love a classic buffalo sauce. I use to make it
the poor man’s way by mixing Frank’s Red Hot with ranch dressing until I learned the original recipe is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better.
Just heat equal parts Frank’s Red Hot and unsalted butter in a pan until melted. Stir occassionally to to keep the
butter from totally separating. If it breaks, just stir again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toss with your cooked wings, let rest for a moment (so the sauce and skin can get to know each other) and dig in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip&lt;/strong&gt;: To store left over buffalo sauce, let it cool first. If it breaks, stir it back together as best as you can
and transfer to the refridgerator immediately. The evenly distributed butter will re-solidify around the hot sauce
making something like a paste. It then won’t be able to break again until re-heated and left to sit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/chicken-wings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/chicken-wings/</guid>
        
        
        <category>modified</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pizza: Putting it together</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t yet, check out the previous pizza posts -&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pizza-intro/&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-dough/&quot;&gt;dough&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-sauce/&quot;&gt;sauce&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final steps along this pizza journey are the choice of toppings and the bake.
Again, the choice oven matters here so I’ll again partition the instructions
to cover both cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;toppings&quot;&gt;Toppings&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to topping a pizza is the ordering of the additions. Put the one item
before another and you could end up with an under or over cooked pizza.
The guidelines for the ordering are based on one fact: too much water will boil toppings and too little will cause them to burn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sauce&quot;&gt;Sauce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your sauce is the dominant source of water among your toppings (especially when your base is just a cheese pie).
Thus, it should go on first and anything you want to protect from the heat should go next so that it can sit
in the water that gently evaporates. Remember from science class, materials under going a phase transition (in this case, liquid to gas)
&lt;em&gt;stay&lt;/em&gt; at the temperature required to transition. So the liquid water in the sauce will never go above 212 F and that will
regulate the temperature that the closest toppings are exposed to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note for traditional ovens&lt;/strong&gt;: The cooking surface should be searing hot already and, if possible, it’s usually useful to
pull the surface out of the oven, put the dough on the surface, and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; top it before putting it all back into the oven again.
The goal is for the crust to cook despite the addition of the sauce. If you had a cooler surface and applied sauce immediately,
the water in the sauce would just start soaking up the heat and the crust would never cook correctly. There are two heat transfers happening -
one between the surface and the crust and the other between the crust and the sauce. A higher temperature difference between surface and crust
will cook the crust quicker but it won’t heat the sauce much quicker (or really, the sauce won’t suck up the heat much quicker).
This is why the 800 F pizza oven users don’t need this warning - their surface is plenty hot to not have to worry about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;herbs-and-other-delicates&quot;&gt;Herbs and other delicates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of your sauce (before the cheese) goes anything delicate with low water content like fresh basil or oregano or even parmesan cheese.
These are all of the items you don’t want to risk burning or even browning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cheese&quot;&gt;Cheese&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next is cheese which will act as an insulating blanket for your delicate toppings. The cheese will save them from the direct heat and
also trap mositure so that they steam rather than roast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can, get a block of whole milk, low-moisture mozzarella. The pre-shredded stuff has additives to keep the shreds from clumping
and these hurt the ability for the cheese to be stretchy like you want in a good pizza slice. The skim/2% cheese doesn’t have enough
fat to keep it from burning in the oven before the crust has cooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use fresh mozzarella as another topping but keep in mind that it contributes more moisture (so higher chance of pizza soup)
and by itself, it can’t act as a barrier to keep your sauce from evaporating away in the oven. Again, there’s a big battle to
keep moisture low but to also not lose too much of it. I find mixing half low-moisture and half fresh mozz is a nice balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/prebake.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plain cheese pie to before entering the oven to give an idea how much cheese and sauce are appropriate.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Plain cheese pie to before entering the oven to give an idea how much cheese and sauce are appropriate.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meats-and-robust-veggies&quot;&gt;Meats and robust veggies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you should add anything that you want to recieve direct heat. This is often meats like peperroni that will crisp up nicely but
vegetables with high water content like peppers, mushrooms, and onions are also important to put on this final layer.
They will roast (which is good for the flavor) but they will also lose their mositure to the hot and dry environment.
If you instead put them under the cheese, the moisture would be trapped under the cheese blanket and you’d (again) have soup-y pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;baking---home-oven-max-550-f&quot;&gt;Baking - Home oven (max 550 F)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For cooking, you want a pre-heated oven as hot as you can get it (usually 500 or 550 F) with your cooking surface pre-heating in it as well.
If you can get your oven to just be on constantly, just do that.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the cooking surface, you want something with high heat capacity like cast iron, a thick baking steal, or a pizza stone
(though some pizza stones don’t like the super high temps so you may risk cracking it). A cookie sheet or aluminum pan is not
going to work well because it has low heat capacity and its temperature will drop drastically after you add the pizza, leading to an undercooked a crust.
As stated eariler, once the surface is heated, I’d recommend taking the cooking surface out of the oven, resting it on the stove, putting
the rolled out dough (with no toppings) onto it, and then topping. This gives the bottom crust a chance to form while you avoid having
to move a fully topped, uncooked pizza.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My only warning is for real broilers. Some ovens say “Broil” and it just means “oven always on” while others have an actual heating
element on the top of the oven. If your oven has the top heating element, it might seem like using it is a good idea to cook toppings.
Maybe to finish the cooking that would be fine but don’t pre-heat your oven with it. The oven itself won’t get to a high enough temp
and you could damage your cooking surface with the close heat. Just treat the high cooking surface temperature as the priority and use
the standard baking mode at its highest possible temperature (convection cooking probably works well but I’ve never had the opportunity to try it).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Top the pizza with sauce (2-3 tablespoons), then delicate herbs (basil, etc that could burn), then cheese (lightly cover and don’t
go overkill - it will melt and spread), then anything that could benefit from direct high heat (pepperoni, mushrooms, peppers, etc).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put it all in the oven and cook until the crust is well browned or the cheese/toppings have cooked - hopefully this happens at the same time. It’s usually 10-15 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;baking---pizza-oven-max-900-f&quot;&gt;Baking - Pizza oven (max 900 F)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow your oven’s instructions to heat. Use an infrared thermometer to track the temperature. My Ooni Fyra has the flame at the
back so the heating is not even but I take ~750 F in the front half of the stone to mean the oven is ready.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use corn flour as the non-sticking agent for your pizza peel then add your dough onto it and give it a good shake forwards and backwards
to make sure it can slide. Add more corn flour where sticking is occuring.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t use regular white flour for this part. It will quickly burn and turn into a sticky substance on the bottom of your crust that does not taste good and sticks to your teeth.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the dough can slide easily on the peel, add the sauce and spread. Then shake again to make sure no sticking has started (it will get harder to fix it
after this point).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add delicate herbs (basil, etc that could burn), then cheese (lightly cover and don’t go overkill - it will melt and spread),
then anything that could benefit from direct high heat (pepperoni, mushrooms, peppers, etc). Shake after you add each part and be quick!
The longer you leave the dough, the stickier it will get and the harder it will be to slide off.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once done with toppings, slide the dough into the oven immediately. Rotate every 30-60 seconds or as one side cooks quicker than the other.
With the crust evenly browned, remove from the oven and enjoy. If your oven has maintained heat, the pizza won’t be in the oven longer than 2-3 minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/inside-ooni.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pizza baking inside my Ooni Fyra.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Pizza baking inside my Ooni Fyra.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we close out this series, I just want to show off the final product a bit below. The dedicated pizza oven
is making an enormous difference here - an extra 300 to 400 degrees will do that. However, the importance of the tedious steps
I’ve outlined becomes apparent: the control of the water content, the time taken to knead, resting the dough overnight, planning
the ordering of toppings. These all help achieve a thin crust that is well cooked, crisp, and not soggy. Meanwhile,
the end-crust has big air pockets and is soft and chewy from the work we did on the gluten structure.
These all hold true in the conventional oven version of this recipe as well - a testament to the fact that anyone
can make good pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/underside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Underside.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Underside.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/side-profile.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Side profile.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Side profile.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-baking/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-baking/</guid>
        
        
        <category>originals</category>
        
        <category>series</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pizza: Sauce</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t yet, check out the previous pizza posts -&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-intro/&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-dough/&quot;&gt;dough&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inspirations&quot;&gt;Inspirations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sauce recipe is based on Bon Appetit’s from their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bonappetit.com/recipe/perfect-pizza&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Making Perfect” Pizza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There’s
really two guiding principle from this recipe that I adopt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pizza sauce is optimally sweet and acidic - flavors which complement the fats from the cheese (and possibly meats) and
the umami/bready flavors of the dough. This is not the time for a rich, deep sauce that’s been on the stove top for 24 hours. That’s
a beautifal bath for meatballs, not a topping for pizza. Pizza is a time for raw tomatoes to shine with just a few light additions to bring things together.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As stated in the introduction, the amount of water on top of our dough can make or break the bake (especially depending on the oven).
Tomatoes already have a lot of water so let’s make sure not to add any more than we need and skip the canning juices.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make slight modifications to the Bon Appetit recipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase the garlic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go by taste and “look” for the salt, olive oil, and black pepper (everyone likes their sauce different) but, in general, increase the salt slightly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Makes about a quart of sauce - good for a 8-10 pizzas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;28 oz can of whole peeled tomatoes (drained of canning liquid)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5-6 thin shavings of fresh garlic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1-2 tbsps olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.5-1 tsp kosher salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Several cranks of fresh black pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;Instructions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine everything but half of the salt (we can add more later but can’t take it away) and then use a hand blender to break down the tomatoes and mix everything.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The olive oil shouldn’t be pooling because there’s so much but you should be able to taste it so adjust to how you prefer.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can use a regular blender or food processor instead.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can leave it a bit chunky if you’d like.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Give the blended mixture a taste and add salt until you’ve switched from thinking “this is sweet and acidic and just tastes like tomatoes” to “oh that’s a little salty.” The final mixture should be a little salty. You’ll notice it because you’re incrementally adding salt and looking for the change. Everyone else is just going to keep asking what makes the sauce taste so good.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can always get a small bowl of the blended tomatoes and add a bit of salt at a time until you get the taste you want and then repeat for the main bowl now that you know what to taste for.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you still don’t believe me about tasting for “a little salty”… If you’ve had bland pizza, I’d be willing to bet it’s because it didn’t have enough salt. The sauce is a way to disperse salt on your pizza evenly. A bite of pizza only has so much sauce but it has to do the job of evenly salting that mouthful. So don’t be stingy and taste as you go!
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Okay, there’s some salt in the dough and in a cured meat topping if you add that but (a) the dough can only be so salty before it hurts the yeast activity and (b) your pepperoni is supposed to raise the salt level, not act as the baseline source of salt.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-sauce/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-sauce/</guid>
        
        
        <category>originals</category>
        
        <category>series</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pizza: Dough</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you haven’t yet, check out the pizza &lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-intro/&quot;&gt;introduction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I explained in the introduction, this recipe was developed for a while using a conventional oven but I now have a
variation built for the temperatures of a dedicated pizza oven. So I’ll split the recipe into two variations when applicable to
cover the capabilities of conventional home ovens (max temp. of ~550 F) and dedicated pizza ovens (max temp. ~900 F).
The only difference in ingredients between these variations is the inclusion of the sugar and olive oil.
Both of these encourage browning and crisping of the crust in a home oven but will cause your pizza to
burn at 700 F and higher. The inclusion of these two ingredients brings us closer to
“NY style” while dropping them is closer to “Neapolitan style” - though pundits of either would nitpick this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the ingredients for the pizza oven are a subset of the ingredients for the home oven, I’ll present
one set of instructions with just an inline note on what to do with the sugar and oil. The rest is all the same!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ingredients&quot;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Makes three 12 inch pies or four 8-10 inch pies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;home-oven-ny&quot;&gt;Home oven (“NY”)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;450g bread (or AP) flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100g double extra fine (“Tipo 00”) flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;4g sugar&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7g yeast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12g kosher salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.5 cups water, heated to 100-110 F&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;u&gt;2 tbsp olive oil (approx.)&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pizza-oven-neapolitan&quot;&gt;Pizza oven (“Neapolitan”)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;450g cups bread (or AP) flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100g double extra fine (“Tipo 00”) flour&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7g yeast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12g kosher salt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.5 cups water, heated to 100-110 F&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;instructions&quot;&gt;Instructions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combine the dry ingredients and wet separately (remember to heat the water - I use the microwave)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you have a stand mixer, you can put the dry mixture into that bowl, turn it on with the dough hook, and pour the liquid mixture in slowly until it comes together.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you don’t have a stand mixer, make hole in the middle of the dry mixture, pour the liquid into the middle, and slowly bring in the walls of flour until combined (this is all just to keep it from being a mess - nothing special about the dough development).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/dough_mixer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dough just after combination of ingredients.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Dough just after combination of ingredients.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just after it’s combined, it should be a bit sticky but not super wet. Let the dough sit for 15 minutes in the covered bowl. After 15 minutes, split it in three to four pieces depending on your desired pie size (I weigh them but up to you).
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If the dough is initially too wet, add some flour and knead it in.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If the dough is a bit dry, just leave it as is unless you’re using a stand mixer - it can be hard to incorporate more water by hand after the initial mixing.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/many_doughs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Separated doughs. To show the difference in texture and shape, the top two rows are unkneaded and the bottom row is kneaded.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Separated doughs. To show the difference in texture and shape, the top two rows are unkneaded and the bottom row is kneaded.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put a little flour on a wooden cutting board and knead the three doughs one at a time. You only want enough flour to keep them from being sticky but they should feel a bit tacky. Depending on how the 15 minute rise goes, they will probably be pretty soft and stretchy. As you knead them, they will become tougher and have a “ripped” texture. Again, they will stay tacky and that’s fine.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The idea is that you are constantly forming and breaking the gluten strands which creates a more complex (and strong) molecular structure that can hold onto air better. Thus it’s easy to under-knead but hard to over-knead.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/kneading.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Kneading technique if you *knead* one.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Kneading technique if you *knead* one.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After you’ve kneaded each dough (1-3 min per dough roughly), pick what you’d like to use as the “top side” and roll the edges of the dough under the top side until you can pinch them together at the bottom. You can pinch and twist the bottom to get it to stay together if the dough is tacky enough.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you’re using a home oven and have already used olive oil, lightly oil the exteriors of the balls with olive oil and put them each in their own containers to rise (deli container, bowl with plastic wrap, w/e).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you’re using a pizza oven and have &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; used olive oil, put the balls into their own containers with no other additions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let them rest in the refrigerator overnight for the best flavor development (trust me when I say it’s a noticeable difference). If you’re trying to move more quickly than that, let them rest at room tempurature for at least an hour. If they are going to sit out for more than 3 hours, just refrigerate them for the whole time.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The dough can stay in the fridge for up to a week (possible longer) - they may grow out of their containers in which case just push it down with your fingers to knock air out and cover it back up.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you’re ready to cook, lightly flour a wooden cutting board, put the dough ball on it and roll/toss it so it gets a light but even coating of flour. At this point, you don’t want the dough to be even tacky (wthat ill make getting it to the cooking surface harder) but you don’t want a bunch of caked on flour either. Once it’s sufficiently coated (you can always add more later), put the dough ball in the center of the surface and push into the center with your fingers and slowly start working the material in the middle of the dough outwards until it starts to form a disk. Once it’s about 6-8 inches in diameter, pick it up by pinching the edge and let gravity pull it down while your hands work around the edge pulling slightly and then rotating the disk. This is the hardest part to describe so best to just look up a couple of good videos. I’d absolutely avoid using a rolling pin (which will push all of the air out).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;table border=&quot;0&quot;&gt;
    &lt;tr style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/dough_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Initial disk shape.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Initial disk shape.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
                &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
                    &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/dough_large.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Final stretched dough.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
                    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;Final stretched dough.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
                &lt;/figure&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all for the dough! I may add a video on it at some point since I think it would be useful to see the kneading and formation steps. Next up is sauce…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-dough/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-dough/</guid>
        
        
        <category>originals</category>
        
        <category>series</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pizza: An introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you’re just interested in the recipes, here are some quick links before I&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;launch into my journey with pizza.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-dough/&quot;&gt;Dough recipe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/RecipeRepo/pizza-sauce/&quot;&gt;Sauce recipe&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;!-- - [Baking steps]({ link _posts/2021-07-28-pizza-baking/2021-07-28-pizza-baking.md }) --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;no-pizza-for-old-men&quot;&gt;No pizza for old men&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the first time I made “pizza” from scratch was in the kitchen of the dorm
building I lived in my first two years at Rutgers. The kitchen had a fridge, oven, range,
sink, cabinets, and counter tops but that was about it. To use it, we had to travel down
to the first floor and bring all of our own supplies and tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t remember what we cooked the “pizza” on but the “dough” was a mixture of mainly
water and pancake mix, very sticky, and put directly into the oven for a pre-bake before
toppings (&lt;em&gt;did we even top it?&lt;/em&gt;). It was terrible and my roommates were overly generous with
their feedback but it was late at night, we only had the dinning hall food to compare to,
and we had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had at other points tried to make actual pizza as God intended but I always bought the dough
from a local pizza shop, messaged it out into a disk, topped it, and stuck it in the oven.
I don’t think it ever came out well because I remember I switched to making calzones which cooked much
better on a baking sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think by this point I’d have given up. &lt;em&gt;Pizza is hard. It’s usually pretty cheap.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Just buy it and leave it to the experts.&lt;/em&gt; That was my thinking for a while but in my senior
year, I got a pizza stone and started trying to make my own dough. The results were fine
but never like what you’d get from a shop. It didn’t help that I was adding cinnamon to the sauce
(&lt;em&gt;what was I thinking?&lt;/em&gt;) and that the stone eventually broke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things didn’t start getting serious though until I moved to Baltimore, Maryland. Being from northern New Jersey,
I had access to some of the best takeout
pizza in the United States due to the proximity to New York City. In Baltimore,
it sudddenly became very difficult to find cheap, takeout pizza that was
any good. Sure, there are some artisinal places that add hot honey and vegan sausage, brie cheese and blueberries,
and the standard overpriced “fresh mozzarella and basil.” But those places start at $16 for a personal pie and
I was a new graduate student with no savings and a regular craving for a $12 large cheese pie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are places that offer that - but they are not good and I would not allow myself to be tricked
into thinking they are. Baltimoreans should take no offense though. I similarly wouldn’t go to New Jersey’s
attempt at LP Steamers. It’s just going to be subpar when compared to the real thing unless someone starts forking over some money.
At that point I realized, if you want something done right, you’ve gotta do it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;there-will-be-pizza&quot;&gt;There will be pizza&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first issue to solve was the baking surface. I considered a new stone but I hate how fragile they are. A baking steel
sounded like a great option but they’re expensive. I finally opted for a Lodge cast iron pizza pan - has handles, holds heat well,
can be used in other scenarios, and it’s nearly indestructable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second issue was the dough. There were no shops that I trusted to sell me good dough and the supermarket sold dough but it was frozen
so there’d have to be planning to buy it ahead of time and let it defrost. The former worked out well many times but what I really wanted
was a better recipe than what I had and that could be ready in just an hour or two. That search led me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foodnetwork.com/recipes/bobby-flay/pizza-dough-recipe-1921714&quot;&gt;Bobby Flay’s dough recipe&lt;/a&gt;. Is this the greatest recipe? No. But the search had to start somewhere and this was the first dough that 
gave consistent results, had a quick rest time, and it’s actually the base for the recipe I use today (though with a 24 hour rest in the fridge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these two solved, the sauce, cheese, and toppings were carried over from my previous experience. For the sauce, I started with a can of crushed tomatoes and additions that
changed over time while I experimented. For the cheese, I either bought pre-shredded, low fat, low moisture mozz or the fresh stuff in the fancy cheese
section. The toppings were a mixture of fresh veggies and Hormel pepperoni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting part to this stage of my pizza journey was the bake. I had a very basic oven which was either “on” or “off”.
No top-down burners. No convenction. “Broil” just meant that the oven never turned off. This meant a maximum oven temp of 550-600 F which is actually pretty hot.
The bake had two steps. The first was just the dough in the oven on the cast iron for a 1-2 minute pre-bake to allow the crust on
the bottom to start browning before the water in the sauce inevtiably acted as a heat sink.
After the pre-bake, the whole pan would come out of the oven (this eventually destroyed my oven mits), the pizza was topped,
and the whole thing returned to the oven for about 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there’s certainly been some fine tuning since then, I’m proud of the pizzas that came out of this method. 
The crust on bottom and at the ends was crisp. The end crust was airy. Everything finished cooking at the right time.
Definitely not the best tasting or prettiest pizzas I’ve ever made but Baltimore takeout had been beaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/OGmethod.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A broccoli and sopressata pizza from a basic oven.&quot; class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;A broccoli and sopressata pizza from a basic oven.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;into-the-pizza&quot;&gt;Into the pizza&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above was my methodology for quite a while until I started paying more attention to pizza related content online.
Youtube videos on classic NY pizza shops/chefs. Posts on food subreddits. The big
one was the Bon Appetit &lt;em&gt;Making Perfect: Pizza&lt;/em&gt; series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were certaint parts of that series that were over-the-top - making your own mozzarella,
buying very expensive San Marzano tomatoes, etc. However, they
made some really good points that got at the heart of what makes a good pizza. Don’t cook your tomatoes ahead of time to keep
the sauce acidic. Use plenty of salt in your dough and sauce. Track how much water you’re incorporating and account
for how that impacts cooking in the oven (they used a 750 F oven so I could have &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; water because cooking times were longer at lower temp).
The Bobby Flay recipe started to change as I incorporated many of the ideas I started to pick up on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-pizza-ultimatum&quot;&gt;The pizza ultimatum&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came Kenji’s New York style pizza (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seriouseats.com/new-york-style-pizza&quot;&gt;recipe&lt;/a&gt;) and the accompanying
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8qU7nRd9fiU&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;. That’s when I went - “Wait… what is that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ooni Koda 16 - an outdoor gas powered pizza oven that could fit on a table top, had oven temperatures in excess of 700 F,
and cooked beautiful pizzas. To that point, I thought you needed an outdoor brick oven, a $1000 Brevil (used in the Bon Appetit series),
or an industrial pizza shop tiered oven. &lt;em&gt;This was an option?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw it in Kenji’s video at the beginning of the pandemic and I immediately started contemplating
if I could buy one. The $500 price tag seemed pretty steep but for $300 there was a smaller one that took wood pellets. I started
researching reviews, looking at pictures, and trying to figure out if it was a good idea (again, a grad student stipend requires some planning).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container-fluid&quot; style=&quot;padding: 0em;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align: center;&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tipping point was when I got burned (literally) by my favorite local artisan pizza place three straight times during pandemic takeout.
Each time, the pizzas had pure black crusts that were beyond edible and I felt too guilty to complain when I knew restaurants
were already struggling. Three times though wasn’t a fluke. Someone saw these pizzas before they made it into the box
and deemed them edible. But by that point, I had paid $120 for six black pies and, &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, grad student stipend doesn’t support
food waste. So I had three options.
Either I was going to go without pizza or I would keep expecting the quality standards to change at the restaurant or I would justify the pandemic purchase of an Ooni
and become my own pizza place. No surprise, it was one of the best purchases I’ve ever made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;col-sm&quot;&gt;
            &lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot; style=&quot;padding: 1.5em&quot;&gt;
                &lt;img src=&quot;/RecipeRepo/assets/images/pizza/Ooni.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My Ooni Fyra pizza oven.&quot; /&gt;
                &lt;figcaption style=&quot;text-align: center; font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;My Ooni Fyra pizza oven.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
            &lt;/figure&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every couple weeks, I make 3-4 nights worth of doughs and have hot-out-of-the-oven pizza for dinner
that beats the snot out of the fast food places and competes with the artisan ones - and it’s &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; cheaper.
I estimate I’ve made about 150 pizzas in it so far and at $16 per pie, that’s $2400 which more than pays
for the oven. My only regret is that I should’ve spent the money and got the Koda 16. It’s bigger 
size would allow for larger pies and the wood pellets leave soot and make it hard to regulate the temperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the story now told, let’s get to the recipes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. What ties the section titles together? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;Pizza variations of 2008 Oscar Nominated films. Why 2008? I don’t know, man. Just let me have fun.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-intro/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://lucascorcodilos.com/RecipeRepo/pizza-intro/</guid>
        
        
        <category>originals</category>
        
        <category>series</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
